in this video we're going to introduce
Clifford algebras also called geometric
algebras for understanding spinners
so far in this series we've looked at
Spinners in three dimensions called poly
Spinners and Spinners and
four-dimensional space time called vial
Spinners we came across these powley
Spinners and vial Spinners almost by
accident by rewriting 3D and 4D vectors
as 2x2 matrices and finding that we
could Factor them into a pair of
spinners
Clifford algebras are useful because
they stop making Spinners look like
accidents
Clifford algebras give us a consistent
recipe for building Spinners in any
Dimension like 3 4 7 or 20 dimensions
this recipe says that Spinners are
members of minimal left ideals and
Clifford algebras
this recipe probably doesn't make much
sense now but it should make sense over
the course of the next few videos
Clifford algebra's also unite many types
of mathematical objects together
in physics we deal with various objects
like scalars vectors bi-vectors linear
maps and spinners
all of these objects live together side
by side in Clifford algebras doing
physics with Clifford algebras feels a
bit like doing physics with the
batteries included
oftentimes everything we need to solve a
problem in physics already lives inside
a Clifford algebra and we don't need to
invent any new mathematical objects to
solve the problem
for example Clifford algebras allow us
to unite the four Maxwell equations of
electricity and magnetism together into
a single equation
the YouTuber suji lacmo has some
fantastic introduction videos for
Clifford algebras and if you're looking
for some more advanced videos on
Clifford algebras you can look at the
bi-vector YouTube channel
for Clifford algebra content on spinners
specifically I'll be referring to this
thesis by Crystal and McKenzie in later
videos I've linked all of these sources
in the description
so what exactly are Clifford algebras
they can be thought of as a
generalization of the complex numbers
quaternions and the sigma matrices
all of these algebraic systems involve
symbols that square to either negative
one or positive one and also involve
symbols where swapping the order of
multiplication gives us a negative sign
this is also called the anti-commutative
property
Loosely speaking Clifford algebras are
algebraic structures where we can square
symbols to plus one or minus one and
also swap their order to get a negative
sign
a good first step for learning Clifford
algebras is to begin by understanding
Grassman algebras also called exterior
algebras I realize I'm throwing a lot of
names out right now but Grassman
algebras can be thought of as a stepping
stone to learning Clifford algebras so
we're going to start with learning
Grassman algebras
the key idea in Grassman algebra is the
wedge product
if we have a vector U and another vector
v their wedge product U wedge V is a
plane segment formed by u and v with an
orientation that follows the arrows
if we swap the order of these vectors
and look at V wedge U we get the same
plane segment but with the opposite
orientation
these oriented plane segments are called
bi-vectors
these bi-vectors are a useful way for
representing rotations and angular
momentum
in introductory physics classes angular
momentum is usually represented using a
vector which you get by using the
awkward right hand rule where you curl
the fingers of your right hand in the
direction of the rotation and stick your
thumb out in the direction of the
angular momentum vector
not only is this awkward but it can lead
to strange geometric results
for example if we reflect a rotating
object in a mirror the angular momentum
Vector points in the opposite direction
this is a very strange behavior for a
vector and indicates we might be doing
something wrong
however when we represent rotations and
angular momentum using bi-vectors
instead the direction of rotation is
immediately obvious and when we reflect
the rotation in a mirror the bi-vector
changes in a predictable way reversing
the orientation in a way that makes
sense
when we have a vector U it's opposite
minus U is a parallel Vector of the same
length but pointing in the opposite
direction when we add U and negative U
together we get zero
similarly when we have a bi Vector U
wedge V it's opposite V wedge U is a
bi-vector of the same size but oriented
in the opposite direction
when we add U wedge V and V wedge U
together we get zero
for this reason we can also write V
wedge U as negative U wedge V because
it's the same bi-vector as U wedge V but
with the opposite orientation
this gives us our first important
property of the wedge product when we
swap the order of the vectors in the
wedge product we get a negative sign in
front
this means that the wedge product is
anti-commutative
when it comes to vectors A vector's
magnitude is equal to the length of its
Arrow if a vector has length 0 we call
it the zero vector
for bi-vectors a bi-vector's magnitude
is equal to the area of its plane
segment if a bi Vector has zero area we
call it the Zero by vector
notice that if we take the wedge product
of two vectors that are parallel we end
up with an area of zero so we get the
Zero by vector
in particular the wedge product of a
vector with itself always gives zero
when we have the wedge product used over
a sum of vectors we can distribute the
wedge product over the sum similar to
The Way We distribute multiplication
over brackets in high school algebra
this has an easy visual interpretation
if we add U1 and U2 and then take the
wedge product with v this is the same
thing as taking U1 wedge V and U2 wedge
V and adding them together into a single
oriented plane
this gives us the distributive
properties of the wedge product
also when we multiply U wedge V by a
scalar like three we can either multiply
the U by 3 or multiply the V by three
mathematically the results are the same
now these results might look different
to you visually however as long as the
areas of the two plane segments are the
same and the orientations are the same
the bi-vectors are considered equal it
doesn't matter if we draw the areas as
squares rectangles parallelograms
circles or some other shape and the
angle or rotation of the shape also
doesn't matter
for example any bi-vector drawn as a
parallelogram can be redrawn as a
rectangle
the portion of the wedge product
involving parallel vectors goes to zero
so we only need the orthogonal portion
of the vectors
also the property of the wedge product
being anti-commutative and the property
of a vector wedged with itself equaling
zero are actually equivalent properties
and can be derived from each other
if we take the anti-commutative property
and set V equals U we get something that
equals the negative of itself which must
be zero so that proves the equivalence
in One Direction
if we instead start with this wedge
product of a sum U plus V with itself
and assume anything wedged with itself
is zero we can distribute to get four
terms two of which go to zero and we're
left with the anti-communitive property
this shows the equivalence in the other
direction
now we've talked about the abstract
properties of bi vectors but I'd also
like to talk about bi-vector components
let's say we're working in 2D space with
basis vectors e x and e y and we're
looking at the bi-vector U wedge V what
are these bi vectors components
we can write u and v as linear
combinations of the basis vectors then
distribute over the wedge product to get
four terms first outer inner last
the ex wedge ex and ey wedge ey terms go
to zero and we can rewrite e y wedge ex
as negative ex wedge ey using the
anti-commutivity of the wedge product
so we find that U wedge V has only one
component with the basis by Vector e x
wedge ey and the component is u x v y
minus u y v x which is the formula for
the area of a parallelogram using Vector
components
there is only one basis bi-vector here
because in the X Y plane there is only
one possible pair of axes
in 3D space the formula for U wedge V
has three components because there are
three possible pairs of axes y z z x and
x y
as an exercise you can try proving that
these are the components
these end up being the same components
that result from the cross product of u
and v
if we continue using the wedge product
we can build higher dimensional
multi-vectors like tri-vectors quad
vectors and so on however we can't keep
going up forever
in three dimensions for example the
tri-vector is the highest we can go if
we include an extra wedge product the
result will always go to zero because
we'll always have a vector wedged with
itself somewhere
also take note that in three dimensions
there is only one trivector possibly
with a scaling constant in front since
we can always swap the basis vectors
into the XYZ order by introducing minus
signs as needed
in space with a given Dimension we can
count the number of basis multi-vectors
of each type just by counting the number
of possible basis Vector combinations
as a result the multi-vectors in a given
Grassman algebra form a sort of diamond
shape with low-grade multi-vectors at
the bottom and high-grade multi-vectors
at the top
every multi-vector has exactly two
possible orientations given by a plus or
a minus sign
we reverse the orientation of a vector
just by flipping the Arrow's Direction
we can build a bi-vector using a set of
vectors all oriented so that the tip of
one touches the tail of the next forming
the boundary of a plane segment
the orientation of this bi Vector just
follows the orientation of the vectors
along the boundary
we can reverse the orientation of the
bifector introducing a negative sign
just by reversing the orientation of the
vectors along the boundary
this logic applies for higher Dimensions
as well we can build a tri-vector using
a set of bi-vectors that form the faces
of a cube
the rule is each bi-vector must be
oriented opposite to its neighbors
wherever they share an edge
if we want to reverse the orientation of
a trivector we just reverse the
orientations of all its bi-vector faces
the approach of using the boundary to
define the orientation of a multi-vector
applies for multi-vectors of all
dimensions
so that's Grassman algebras which are
algebraic structures over Vector spaces
that use the wedge product to build
multi-vectors
now what's a Clifford algebra Loosely
speaking it's an algebra where symbols
Square to either plus 1 or -1 and
flipping the order of symbols introduces
a negative sign similar to what we saw
with Grassman algebras
this multiplication rule is called the
Clifford product or geometric product
which is denoted by writing symbols next
to each other like this
we'll soon see that this leads us to the
complex numbers the quaternions the
sigma matrices and their generalizations
instead of starting with a formal
definition of Clifford algebras I'm
going to go through a few examples and
then I'll give a definition at the end
so let's look at some examples of
Clifford algebras which are algebras
with symbols that square two plus one or
-1
let's say we have a symbol I that
squares 2 minus one
one way to approach this is to interpret
this as a matrix problem saying that the
number one is actually the identity
Matrix and the symbol I is actually a
matrix like this that squares to the
negative identity
the expression a plus IB would then give
you a matrix like this
another way to approach this is to
Simply treat I as its own symbol with i
squared equals negative one as the
definition
this is the more traditional approach
and it's how we normally Define complex
numbers
what we have here is the Clifford
algebra
cl01 because we have zero symbols that
square two positive one and a single
symbol that squares two negative one so
the complex numbers also called cl01 are
a first example of a Clifford algebra
so we have two options for looking at
Clifford algebras we can either look at
them using matrices or we can look at
them using abstract symbols now we
normally take the second approach of
abstract symbols as the more Pure or
correct definition of the complex
numbers and we prefer it over the Matrix
approach
the reason is there are an infinite
number of matrices of all different
sizes that square to the negative
identity Matrix we say that these are
all Matrix representations of the
abstract symbol I
but we don't actually need any of these
Matrix representations to do math with
complex numbers it's often simpler to
just take the symbol I as its own object
and forget about matrices
as an exercise you can try multiplying
the expression a plus IB times C plus ID
in both Matrix form and symbolic form
and show that they give equivalent
results
here's another example of a Clifford
algebra let's say that we have a symbol
J which squares two plus one again we
can interpret this as a matrix problem
saying one is the identity Matrix and J
is a matrix like this that squares to
the identity
so the expression a plus J B would
correspond to this Matrix here
but once again there are an infinite
number of matrices of all sizes that
square to the identity a simpler
approach is to just treat J as its own
symbol with J squared equals plus one as
the definition
this is the Clifford algebra cl10
because it has a single symbol that
squares two plus one and zero symbols
that square two minus one this is also
called the split complex numbers
here's another example we have three
symbols Sigma X Sigma Y and sigma Z that
all square 2 positive one
but since we now have more than one
symbol we now also need to decide how
these symbols will multiply with each
other let's take some inspiration from
Grassman algebras let's say that when we
multiply two of these Clifford algebra
symbols together we can flip their order
if we include a minus sign
if we approach this as a matrix problem
we get the sigma matrices or Pali
matrices that we spent a lot of time
talking about in videos six to ten but
the Clifford algebra style approach is
to forget about the matrices and just
treat these three sigmas as their own
symbols that square two positive one and
anti-commute with each other
actually if you were to go back and
watch video number six which covers
Sigma matrices in detail you'll notice
that almost everything in the video can
be figured out without writing down any
matrices and just using these squaring
and anti-commutative properties of the
sigmas
again the sigma's only approach is seen
as simpler because we can get all the
same results without worrying about
matrices
this gives us the Clifford algebra cl30
because we have three symbols that
square two plus one and zero symbols
that square two minus one and the three
symbols also anti-commute with each
other
this is also called the algebra of
physical space
pairs of different sigmas give us the bi
vectors in cl30 and it turns out these
are completely equivalent to the
quaternion imaginary units i j k
the reasons IJ and K anti-commute with
each other is rooted in the fact that
the sigma pair bi-vector is also
anti-commute with each other
we say that the quaternions are the even
grade sub-algebra of cl30 because they
only involve the grade zero scalar and
the grade 2 bi-vectors
here is one final example with four
symbols gamma zero Gamma 1 gamma 2 and
gamma 3. gamma zero squares 2 positive
one and the other three Gammas Square
two negative one and all the Gammas
anti-commute with each other
treating this as a matrix problem we can
get these matrices which are called the
Dirac matrices or gamma matrices
these will pop up if you've ever studied
the Dirac equation for particle physics
or Quantum field Theory
and again there are multiple Solutions
this set of matrices is called the
chiral basis or vial basis there's also
this alternative solution called the
mass basis or Dirac basis
but as usual I'm going to say it's
better to just treat the Gammas as their
own symbols that obey these squaring and
anti-commutative properties and take
those as the definition this gives us
the Clifford algebra cl13 because we
have one symbol that squares two plus
one and three symbols that square two
minus one this is also called the
space-time algebra
suji lacmo has a great video showing how
this can be used to formulate special
relativity Linked In the description
so generally speaking we say that the
Clifford algebra clpq is in algebra with
P symbols that square two plus one and Q
symbols that square two minus one
and the symbols all anti-commute with
each other
sometimes if Q equals zero and there are
no symbols that square two minus one we
can omit the Q in our notation and just
write CLP for a Clifford algebra with P
symbols that square two plus one and
anti-commute
I should mention that this
anti-commutation relation is sometimes
written like this with curly braces and
the dot product or metric
if the two symbols are different these
two terms in the sum cancel and we get
zero since the dot product of orthogonal
vectors is zero if the two symbols are
the same we get twice the vectors
squared length
as a quick aside sometimes in Clifford
algebras we also include symbols that
square to zero if we have a symbol
Epsilon that squares to zero we can
again interpret this as a matrix problem
where zero is the zero Matrix and
Epsilon is a matrix that squares two
zero like this
but it's more common to treat Epsilon as
its own symbol with Epsilon squared
equals zero as the definition
these are called the Dual numbers in
Clifford algebra notation we call this
cl001 where the first two numbers tell
us how many symbols Square two plus one
and minus one and the third number tells
us how many symbols Square two zero
these won't come up very often in this
video series but it's useful to know
about
so let's compare the wedge product from
Grassman algebras to the Clifford
product in Clifford algebras
now with Grassman algebras I was often
talking about vectors in Clifford
algebras I was Loosely talking about
symbols but we're going to interpret
these symbols as basis vectors in
Clifford algebras
for example with the sigma matrices cl30
we can think of the three symbols as
forming a 3D orthonormal basis
this is how we've been treating the
sigma matrices in previous videos
with Grassman algebras the wedge product
of a vector with itself always gives
zero because the resulting plane segment
has an area of zero with Clifford
algebras taking the Clifford product of
a vector with itself gives that vectors
squared magnitude
unit vectors in our orthonormal basis
Square two plus one or -1 because they
have a length of one
likewise a vector of length 5 will
Square two plus or minus 25.
if you're confused about why a vector
would Square to negative one this ends
up being useful in special relativity
when we need to tell the difference
between time-like vectors and space-like
vectors
with Grassman algebras anytime we have a
wedge product of two vectors we can
always flip their order if we include a
negative sign which is the
anti-commutative property
for Clifford algebras the
anti-communitive property applies only
for orthogonal vectors
for the sigmas sigma X Sigma Y and sigma
Z are all orthogonal so they all
anti-commute with each other but a given
Sigma will not anti-commute with an
arbitrary vector v which is not
orthogonal to it
let's look at the Clifford product of
two vectors in cl20 where the ex and ey
basis vectors both Square two plus one
we can write vectors u and v in terms of
this basis
we can then write the Clifford product U
times V using distributive properties
first out inner last and get four terms
the terms with e x squared and e y
squared both go to plus one so we get a
sum of scalars
since e x and e y are orthogonal we can
flip e y times e x to get Negative e x
times e y using anti-commutivity we can
then group these two terms together
so the Clifford product of two vectors
is the sum of a scalar and a bi-vector
the scalar part looks like the dot
product of u and v and the bi-vector
part looks like the wedge product of u
and v
so loosely speaking the Clifford product
can be thought of as a combination of
the dot product and the wedge product
when we take the Clifford product of two
orthogonal vectors u and v the dot
product goes to zero and we're left with
just the wedge product so we get to use
the anti-commutivity of the wedge
product in this special case
when we take the Clifford product of two
parallel vectors u and v the wedge
product part goes to zero and we get U
dot V which also equals V Dot U due to
the commutivity of the dot product
and remember the dot product of a vector
with itself gives that vectors squared
length
before I finish the video I'm going to
go over some more abstract definitions
of Grassman algebras and Clifford
algebras that involve tensor algebras
and quotients this is a little more
advanced and you probably don't need to
worry about it if you're a beginner with
Clifford algebras I'm just including
this section for completeness for those
who want to know about it
I've already talked about the tensor
product in video number eight as a basic
review the tensor product is like an
abstract generalization of the outer
product of a column vector and a row
vector
it obeys distributive properties over
addition just like array multiplication
and distributivity works in both
directions
and when multiplying by a scalar we can
either give the scalar to the left hand
side or the right hand side
we can create tensor products of 2 3 4
or any number of vectors
now I'll introduce the tensor algebra
let's say that we have a two-dimensional
Vector space V with basis vectors E1 and
E2
the tensor algebra of V denoted Tia V
includes scalars all the vectors in V
all the tensor products of two vectors
in V all the tensor products of three
vectors in v and so on up to Infinity
as we increase the number of tensor
products the number of possible terms
increases exponentially
individual vectors live in the vector
space V Vector pairs live in V tensor V
also written V squared Vector triples
live in V tensor V tensor V or V cubed
and so on
scalars live in the set of scalar's s
which is sometimes written as V to the
power of zero
in tensor algebras we can add together
arbitrary elements from this infinite
collection so we can write expressions
like two plus three e one minus 5 E2
tensor E1 tensor E2
now let's try modifying our tensor
algebra with a special rule
we're going to say that anytime we see a
vector tensored with itself it will go
to zero
this leaves scalars unchanged and also
leaves individual vectors unchanged
but with tensor products of two vectors
E1 tensor E1 and E2 tensor E2 now get
sent to zero
but as we proved earlier the property of
a vector product with itself equaling
zero automatically implies that we can
swap the order of a product if we
introduce a negative sign so using this
new rule E1 tensor E2 equals negative E2
tensor E1
for the tensor product of three vectors
it turns out every single term goes to
zero since all terms contain at least
one pair of identical basis vectors this
applies for any larger tensor products
as well
so using this new rule we've eliminated
a huge number of infinite tensor
products and we're left with only four
what we're left with is exactly the
rules for The Grassman algebra
so abstractly The Grassman algebra is
what we get when we start with the
tensor algebra and apply the Special
Rule that any Vector tensored with
itself goes to zero
more formally we say that The Grassman
algebra is what we get when we take the
quotient of the tensor algebra by the
ideal generated by V tensor V
we can start over and do this again but
with a slightly modified rule where we
take any Vector tensored with itself and
instead of setting it to zero we set it
to that vector's squared length
using this Rule scalars and individual
vectors are unaffected E1 tensor E1 and
E2 tensor E2 are now equal to the scalar
one
this property also results in the
anti-commutative property if two vectors
are orthogonal
this is because orthogonal vectors obey
a Pythagoras formula which allows us to
cancel the terms from both sides of this
equation
and so because E1 and E2 are orthogonal
we get that E2 tensor E1 equals negative
E1 tensor E2
for the terms with three vectors in the
product any identical vectors get sent
to the scalar plus one so we're left
with just individual vectors which we
already have in our algebra
in fact any more complicated combination
of vectors will always give us either
scalars vectors or bi-vectors so again
we've removed all the higher infinite
number of terms and we're left with only
four terms
this is exactly the Clifford algebra
cl20 where vectors Square to their
squared magnitudes and orthogonal
vectors anti-commute
so abstractly the Clifford algebra is
what we get when we start with the
tensor algebra and apply the Special
Rule that any Vector tensored with
itself goes to its squared length
more formally we say that the Clifford
algebra is what we get when we take the
quotient of the tensor algebra by the
ideal generated by the tensor V minus
the squared magnitude of V
you might also see this magnitude
formula written with a G this is called
the metric tensor and it's just a
function that gives Vector lengths
so to conclude a Clifford algebra also
called a geometric algebra is what we
get when we take a vector space and
allow multiplication between vectors
using the Clifford product also called
the geometric product
the Clifford product of a vector with
itself gives that vectors squared
magnitude and the Clifford product of
two orthogonal vectors is
anti-communitive so we can swap the
order if we include a negative sign in
the next video we're going to see how we
can use Clifford algebras to build spin
groups in any Dimension these are groups
that double cover the rotation group in
a given Dimension and do rotations and
lorentz boosts using double-sided
transformations